Guide to the Nina Cornelia Mitchell Papers, 1854-1958
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nina Cornelia Mitchell papers 1854-1958
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mitchell, Nina Cornelia, 1854-1958.
Extent: 4,067 Items
Chiefly family correspondence, including that of Miss Mitchell, of Flushing, N.Y., and Shepherdstown, W. Va., relating to her relief work in Europe during and after World War I. Topics include U. S. Army camps, British Expeditionary Forces hospitals and nurses in France, refugees in Italy, various organizations for wounded soldiers, such as Le Phare de France, and the role women played in relief work. Some letters after World War I relate to continued European relief work and the Food for France Fund. Other correspondence includes that of John Fulton Berrien Mitchell, Sr., an officer in the 2nd New York Volunteer Cavalry, 1862-1864, concerning ordnance and camp and garrison equipage.
RL.00926
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Nina Cornelia Mitchell Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1970.
Collection Overview
Chiefly family letters; genealogical material; Civil War papers of John Fulton Berrien Mitchell, Sr., an officer in the 2nd New York Volunteer Cavalry, 1862-1864, concerning ordnance and camp and garrison equipage; and letters concerning European travel in the 1870s; life in Columbia University during the early 1900s; life in France, Italy, and England and the United States during World War I; British Expeditionary Forces hospitals and nurses; treatment of wounded soldiers, especially the work among the blind of an organization called Le Phare de France; war work by women; postwar relief work; the Food for France Fund; life in Paris during the 1920s; and Sufism.
Correspondents include John Fulton Perrien, Jr.; Henry Bedinger; Edward Bedinger Mitchell; Nina Cornelia (Mitchell) Wickham (the aunt of Nina Cornelia Mitchell); Gladys Elliott; Winifred Holt; and John Fulton Berrien Mitchell, Jr.
There are also a few miscellaneous legal and financial papers and miscellaneous invitations, calling cards, school exercises by John Berrien Mitchell, Sr., at Columbia College, 1860-1861; report cards, 1890s, for Stephen H. Dandridge at Shepherd College; solicitations from charities clippings; and diaries and miscellaneous writings by various family members, especially by Nina Cornelia Mitchell about her experiences, particularly in Europe. One diary, 1860, by Sarah P. (Berrien) Mitchell describes a trip to Lake Superior and the mines which she saw there. There are also photographs of family members and of their homes.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Mitchell, John Fulton Berrien, b. 1878; Food for France Fund; Le Phare de France; United States -- Army -- History -- World War, 1914-1918; United States -- Army -- New York Cavalry Regiment, 2nd (1861-1865); United States -- Army -- Officers -- Correspondence; Women and war; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- Hospitals; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Europe -- History -- 1918-1945; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Equipment and supplies
Contents of Collection
- Nina Cornelia Mitchell Papers, 1854-1958, (27 boxes, 1 oversize folder)
  - Correspondence, 1854-1899 (including Civil War accounts and reports of J.F.B. Mitchell) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1816 September 4-1915 June 30 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1916 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1915 July 4-1928 January 5 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1918 May (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1918 June-1919 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1921 July (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1921 August-1922 April (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1922 May-1923 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1927 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1934 June (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1924 July-1940 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1941 May 26-1950 December 14 and undated. (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1958 and undated. (Box 14)
  - Legal papers (Box 15)
  - Financial papers, 1907-1940s
  - Miscellany, 1858-1919 and undated.
  - French documents (Box 16)
  - Beliefs and Membership Application of Ku Klux Klan
  - Writings
  - Financial papers
  - Clippings
  - Printed materials
  - Notebooks and diaries
  - Writings (Box 17)
  - Calling Cards (Box 18)
  - Printed materials
  - Clippings
  - Photographs: Various friends and relatives of Mitchell family (Box 19)
  - European photographs
  - Miscellaneous photographs
  - Postcards
  - Photographs: William Mitchell & Edward Elbert Mitchell and their families (Box 20)
  - Photographs: Various homes (Box 21)
  - Photographs: Miniatures and miscellaneous photographs (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Mitchell Family (Box 23)
  - Diaries (Box 24)
  - Volume: "A Short Memoir of Reverend Edward Mitchell by his son William Mitchell" (Box 25)
  - Volume: Photograph Album, 1860s (Box 26)
  - Volumes (miscellaneous) (Box 27)
  - Oversize materials (Opaperfolder 1)